Well, we're ready to get going with our brand new project, so I hope you are ready to level up your
programming skills.
All right, first things first.
As this is a new game, we need to create a new project.
And the good news is that it's actually quite easy.
But firstly make sure that your current project is saved.
Now it does do this automatically, but if you're about to quit your tab or close your computer, just
click the Save Now button.
If you don't see the button, it just means that your project is already saved.
So with it saved, all we need to do is click the scratch button here and then click create.
And once more we have a brand new project.
And we also have this cat free of charge.
But unfortunately for the cat, we don't need it in this project so we can delete it.
Also, as you can see, our project is just called untitled, so we can also name it.
We'll call it Soccer header game.
Yeah, I know it's not really a creative name, but you can name it whatever you like.
Although it's a good idea to name your program something that makes it easy for you to identify and
find them later.
Now with that done, we are ready.
But before we dive right in, remember how in the previous section we talked about the importance of
breaking down a big project like building a game and smaller achievable steps.
We do this because it not only makes the process more manageable, but will also help you develop good
programming habits and even life habits.
It's sort of like climbing a mountain.
If you're at the bottom and you're looking right up to the top, it honestly seems impossible.
But if you just look forward ten steps, you think to yourself, yeah, I could walk those ten steps,
and then you look forward to another ten steps and you walk those ten steps, and before you know it,
you're at the top of the mountain.
And the same is true with programming.
We are just tackling this mountain of a game by dividing it into a series of smaller steps.
So for this game.
Thankfully it isn't too large and complex, but we can still break it down.
So let's begin by making a simple soccer header game where the player moves a character to keep a ball
in the air.
Now we'll be using assets found in the scratch library, including our main character Ben, a soccer
ball sprite, and a soccer field backdrop called soccer two.
Because this mountain of a game is not too big.
It's sort of more like a hill than a mountain.
We can divide it into just three steps.
The steps are setting up the basic structure, developing the gameplay mechanics, and polishing the
game.
First we set up the basic structure, so we'll bring in all the necessary assets, like sprites and
backdrops, to set up the game's foundation.
Now, for even bigger games, you might break this stage down into smaller tasks like building the start
screen, then the main character or specific game elements.
Second, we have to develop the gameplay mechanics.
So once we have the essential elements in place, we can begin programming the game mechanics.
Now we'll need to code the character movement, the ball physics, and interactions between the character
and the ball.
And then finally we have the polish and refine stage.
So after the core mechanics are working, we can add more details like sound effects and animations
and even scorekeeping.
And this is also when we'll thoroughly play and test the game, making any necessary adjustments to
ensure it's enjoyable and engaging.
Well with this very important concept out of the way, I want you to try and complete the first stage
by yourself, which is bringing in all the necessary assets.
Remember, these are our main character a soccer ball sprite and a soccer field backdrop called soccer
two.
So pause the video and try and see if you can do this.
If you tried it by yourself.
Well.
Well done.
Well, let's see how it's done.
Firstly, we can import our two sprites into our scratch project.
So clicking this add a sprite button.
We can simply search for Ben.
And here he is.
Next we can click it again and search for the ball.
Over here is another soccer ball we can use.
And finally there is the backdrop.
And for this we can just click here and choose soccer two.
And there you have it.
The first stage is done.
You have successfully set up the foundation for your soccer header game.
And we are ready to start breathing life into our sprites with code.
But as we continue to develop this game and every game and project you work on here after, remember
the importance of breaking a big problem down into smaller steps, because when you do this, really
nothing is impossible.
Even climbing Mount Everest can be done.